[Laughter]
[Music]
welcome back I am one of those laymen
pascal's you've heard about this is the
interval stage series in conversation
with people who seemingly can't stop
themselves from communicating about
transformative integrative and emergent
multi-dimensional themes through
podcasts YouTube videos and other online
formats who are these people what do
they point towards and how can we help
connect them clarify them and amplify
them if that is they actually do
comprise of them of some kind here to
help us explore this terrain today is
Daniel Thorson who for some reason I
always use the full name of Daniel
Thorson get us started by telling people
where they can find your online content
sure my podcasts that I host it's called
emerge and you can find it probably the
best place to find it is on w-w-what is
emerging calm slash podcast that's very
interesting ganga Thorson
Thank You Lena Pascale bring your words
what do you think it accomplishes and
what would you love for it to accomplish
oh man yeah I mean typically the only
framing of my work
that seems sustainable is that I'm
having conversations with people that I
find fascinating that I'm curious about
and increasingly that I experience some
kind of like erotic pull towards not
sexual but just like I want to get to
know what it is that they how they see
the world and as soon as I put any kind
of like loftier vision of what it is
that I'm doing I noticed that the
excitement for myself around the project
starts to dry up so I try to keep it
pretty simple like that and in terms of
what I hope it accomplishes I mean my
dream my dream would be that
listen to it and like have a sense of
taking greater responsibility for their
life that's not yeah since you have an
obvious spiritual or religious
orientation do you think of these
conversations when they work well as
being a kind of extended Sangha for me
certainly yeah I mean the network that I
found myself embedded in since I've
started the emerge project is profound
and and you know I just came out of a
seventy five day retreat and it was it
was interesting because on the one hand
I came out into my physical community
here at the monastic Academy I was kind
of received and I got to sort of
reintegrate into that whole and at the
same time I started to kind of enter
back into this online new sphere this
global or planetary Sangha that I found
myself now to be a part of and so it's
been very interesting to have those two
reentry's happen side by side so it
certainly functions as a kind of
extended Sangha for me
I don't know to what degree it does for
others you know the unfortunate fact is
that podcasting is a broadcast medium
and Sangha for me I think has to be
two-way or you know omnidirectional to
really be Sangha so yeah I think
something like that in myself which is
what I asked you know I I'm split
between on the one hand thinking of
Dharma its broadest sense as being an
existing body of wisdom to learn and
receive and on the other hands a set of
conversational skills that allows wisdom
to be regenerated within any cultural or
historical context as long as the my
conversations are going on hmm beautiful
yeah I mean I love that one of one of my
teachers Rob birdy who just recently
passed away talks about this
simultaneity of creating and discovering
right so we're constantly creating and
discovering they're not actually set
we've got word really that means both of
those things at once so we have to say
create and discover
and that that for me is very much a part
of call it a religious movement but what
this is all about for me why call it
emerge the honest answer is that I used
to work for a company called Buddhist
geeks which was like a kind of og
podcasting media company and my friend
Vince horn who started it I was with him
as he explored the limits of Buddhism as
a container for his inquiry and ran up
against the limits of that and started
to kind of almost represent Buddhism
even though when he started it he loved
Buddhism it was the love of his life
and so I very conspicuously and
intentionally picked a kind of container
or a title or framing that would never
feel constraint and so emerge is this
kind of sense of like oh there's always
something new there's always some new
way of seeing there's always some new
way of being in relationship to life or
to the world or to others that I can
explore and that's calling me forward
there's always some new complexities and
they're nuanced and I don't know where
that's going to come from you know it
might come from sociology it might come
from primitive skills it might come from
philosophy it might come from theology
it might come from technology it might
come from some emerging discipline I
don't even know about yet and I want to
be free to explore them all nice very
open yeah yeah there's a lot of
philosophies around emergence as sort of
the leading edge of the development of
the universe but there's also this sense
in which emerging is the alternative to
asserting something where if you just
sort of inspect what's there and see
what you can find in it then what
emerges is something more pure more
embodied richer than if you've just made
an assertion and I think I heard you say
somewhere that you
you sort of have an allergy to
totalizing narratives we can makes me
think of you you know working in a
medium where you're open to organic
richness and deviance and complexity and
plurality in the conversation what I
wonder is has that always been an
attitude you've had or is that a kind of
a the result of some insights that
you've developed over time as a result
of insights I've had over time I used to
be a very totalizing kind of in my own
way fundamentalist sort of personality I
was kind of known for it actually I was
in I was a first ranked member of the
debate team in my college and I would
kind of intellectually humiliate people
through my kind of like almost looking
back on a kind of authoritarian
perspective-taking and I was very good
at that and I actually got rewarded for
it and I was you know I kind of loved it
because I valid validated in some kind
of my intellectual identity I had but I
think really once I started meditating
in earnest and and that their theory of
mind and kind of really contemplated how
I want to be alive then that quickly
fell away it became obvious that taking
a totalizing perspective or reducing the
way things are into any single narrative
or conceptual vision is just a kind of
violence on life that not only isn't
true but for me more importantly just
destroys beauty and aliveness which are
to a large degree what I want to uplift
I in everything I do nice what do you
think are the skills required to have a
good conversation that's such a
beautiful question
first impulse is to just put back on you
and ask you where your you're coming
from with that I mean there's how
dialogical is this meant to be actually
I'd like to know oh we could go as far
as you like in either direction hmm okay
I mean if you want to go back and forth
I'm fine with it to really answer that
question I would have to know what you
mean by good conversation like what's in
what's in that for you what's wrapped up
in that yeah I would kind of think of it
in two senses on the one hand like a
colloquial sense of a good conversation
where when you're done you feel richer
you feel more energized you feel like
waste your time in predictable modes
nobody would suck anybody else's energy
or sabotage did and it got somewhere you
didn't expect but on the other hand hmm
you know Plato talks with Socrates
there's a sense that a conversation can
sometimes get you to a place that is
transcendental wherein equivalent or
even exceeds sometimes your own personal
practice so both of those is what I mean
either mmm yeah yeah and I would add a
third to and sometimes a good
conversation completely destroys you
like it precipitates an existential
crisis right and I think those that
that's one that I'm longing to get
better at personally but so if I
consider those three well I I don't know
I mean this is an ongoing and open
inquiry for me and a lot to a large
degree it's why I started the podcast
was to learn better how to have good
conversations of least of a certain
variety good intellectual conversations
I think the grounded and embodied I hmm
I'll say that for the purposes of my
podcast I know but I'm having a good
conversation because my energy body is
progressively harmonized over the course
of the dialogue we're bye-bye to the end
I'm basically a hair's breadth away from
the state of Samadhi or concentration
like I could sit down and everything
would just be flowing and I think part
of the reason that that happens is that
and and part of what constitutes a good
conversation is that I'm constantly
speaking on behalf of that which seems
most meaningful and relevant to the
discursive the dialogical space and so
to the degree that you don't do that or
I don't do that that seems to kind of
ossify my energy and then the
conversation doesn't feel as good and
whatever is meant to be said in that
service it doesn't get fed and it you
can kind of feel it in that field and
that doesn't feel good
so you're navigating by feeling and
trying to serve the context and
remembering the the opening that's
available for what this conversation is
supposed to become like leaving that
space for it totally yeah and I think
the most important thing is that I I
don't I do what I can to try not to get
too much in my head which is interesting
I think because people listen to the
podcast the conversations I have my
podcast and they it seems very heady a
lot of people tell me they can't listen
to it because it's like too intellectual
but the actual experience for me of
participating in the conversations is
one of deep embodiment typically where
I'm actually just like feeling my way
like I will feel like I don't understand
something and there oh what don't I
understand my body will tell against
something and then the words will come
into my head and then I'll speak them
but it comes from the body it doesn't
come from like the head out of my mouth
it comes like I think it comes from my
body up into my head and out my mouth
and as soon as I make it like head to
mouth just head to mouth the
conversation gets real
I feel and yeah boring and what's
interesting to me when when a very
embodied conversation is perceived by
someone else to be too heady and it
often tells you more about the listener
about the speaker title they remember
hearing a poet say that he became a poet
because he didn't have enough
imagination to do mathematics you're
going at ideas with heart and body then
you can take heart and body up and it's
an amazing idea around this but if
someone else isn't doing that they just
hear amazing idea realms and kind of gap
out totally I know I know yeah I got
like chills all over my body and this is
something that I am so alive with is
that ideas can be this erotic landscape
of embodied experience but so many
people especially in the spiritual
circles of the modern West I think tend
to just be like concepts are anti
spiritual antibody and if you're dealing
in that kind of world then you're like
not practicing or that's that's not what
this is all about that's problem you
know get away from concepts and that's
been one of the kind of baselines of my
podcast is basically trying to disrupt
that I think really naive perspective on
concepts the problem is that typically
the way you disrupt that astute concepts
and the people that are really holding
to that perspective I suspect really
encounter you know these these very
persuasive in my opinion and and well
thought through lines of arguments but
it's it's to their own detriment because
honestly like the landscape of beauty
that conceptuality opens up is enormous
I mean and it's such a such a tragedy I
think that so many people in the
spiritual world act you have a concept
that tells them that concepts are not
relevant to spirituality it's very sad
to me yeah self-sabotage at every level
is possibly yeah you were talking about
wanting to get into conversations that
precipitate a crisis and maybe destroy
you hmm
now were you thinking more
terms of your skill of destroying
someone in a conversation or reopening
together oh oh I would love to be
destroyed I mean both you know I mean I
think that's really what I had a
conversation with Andrew Taggert on my
podcast one last conversations I
recorded and we talked about this but
essentially there's a way I think of
speaking to each other that doesn't let
your conversational partner turn away
from the truth and integrity of their
heart and often if somebody like manages
holds your holds your face in it for
long enough you'll you'll you'll you'll
often break open to new understandings
of how your life how you typically how
you've been living out of integrity with
what you know to be true and I I'll of
it when that happens I mean part of me
hates it you know part of me does not
want to do that but I'm always
appreciative in the from a longer longer
term perspective when somebody does that
and I'd like to get better at that
myself with supporting people and not
looking away from their integrity yeah
it's a fine line because there are seems
like a lot of people who their ego
prides themselves on their ability to
interfere with others for the sake of
what they think is the truth mm-hmm yeah
yeah right well that's exactly what
makes it such a let's say artful process
right because if you do that and that's
that's just more there's a
thing obviously Zen history is full of
these fragments of conversations that
were thought to have facilitated made
non-duality visceral and contagious
let's say what what have you noticed
about conversations that you've been in
in your life we're in the conversation
you felt like some other transmission
came across to you but one place where
that happens
quite often for me is here at the Manasa
Academy in the interview room you know
when I'm working with the teacher here
so are you for all and he would be a
great person to have on some kind of
podcast to ask that question to he comes
from a Zen background and more generally
it seems to be the case that that
happens to the degree that both parties
are holding this stance of being more or
less unwilling to look away from what is
true now true is a very difficult word
to use with a straight face but to you
know there's there's a sense that that
both parties are really I mean I think
it better PI better to put them in the
negative and unwilling to each
other yeah and then something something
can sometimes arise there is my
experience but man if I could make it
happen more often I would love to know
exactly how that meat gets made what do
you what do you think I know you got me
curious
yeah well I mean if I look at that Zen
history there's obviously a peculiar
style of phrasing that they're using the
people have to have the degree of being
that enables that to have it but they're
sure then about that we call it
paradoxical or whatever but there's
something about putting putting focus on
something where there's no room to move
and also suspecting all the answers
might be in that trap and on so I think
shifting context if you read all those
Zen parable cases very often the next
person who speaks comes at it from a
completely different angle
then they get hit by another angles in
this kind of radical perspective
shifting I was gonna ask about that
because I wonder about the degree to
which moving among different types of
truths facilitates the Harmonized
experience and the higher possibilities
of discourse like it
person is bringing sensations and
feeling and ideas or moving back and
forth between spiritual and material or
or whatever the domains are the moving
among domain and facilitated yep I think
so I think so I mean that is fundamental
to my you know spirituality I suppose is
really playing with different ways of
looking or different ways of relating to
whatever it is right but understanding
that the way of looking itself the
object whatever it is the idea the
situation arises dependently with how
you look at it and so by kind of like
shifting perspectives or shifting ways
of looking shifting ways that we
relating we actually give rise I think
to a richer thing whatever it is that
we're playing with right and so in terms
of building a rich conversation yeah
it's indispensable if you're locked into
one perspective I mean I hope it's a
good one yeah I don't have a question
about this but I just wanted to bring it
up because it's something that's always
at the edge of my thinking about
conversations which is a moment or a
degree to which that richness that's
been built up or discovered starts to
become a layer as if it was a third
participant in the conversation and
whether I have a responsibility to sort
of shift into a relationship to that
once it's there mmm that's great
yeah I find it very useful teacher to
bring to presence that personally how do
you how do you usually work with that
question or that tension well it's I
don't I'm not satisfied with the degree
to which I work with it because usually
I it's clear to me in retrospect after
the conversation I think oh it was
definitely never I'm walk away with it
afterwards but I think what could I have
done
in the speech other than be peripherally
aware of it you know calling out mention
it is that enough what would the next
step be yeah my sense is that it's a
really powerful move if you're
attempting to kind of create this third
almost like biological entity amongst
the participants because what I notice
is that if I'm feeling it if I'm sensing
it and then I name it the other
participant can also then name it sense
it and we can actually develop some more
coherence around the naming of it and
that if if we're all Co sensing it then
that is typically what takes the whole
thing to another octave usually away
from a little bit it dampens though our
my experience it dampens our individual
like agency perspective a little bit
though it tends to start amplifying this
it tends towards more like unity
consciousness and things like that which
is great you know you have choices to
make I suppose yeah I'm always concerned
about the what the relationship is
between the structural capacity of a
relationship or a group of people and
versus their ability to get into higher
mutual harmonies with each other because
I've seen a lot of groups get to a place
that is amazing in their interest
subjective communion but then I've seen
it not necessarily become anything in
any of their lives and I know there's a
lot of groups that can function together
in very intelligent ways that don't
necessarily get that experience with
each other hmm yeah what do you make up
that discrepancy I mean I I sort of have
to just imagine they're two different
epistemological domains with their own
sets of practices and procedures but in
my heart I feel like there's a better
interface and I feel like it'll be a way
of of holding and questioning the
emergent mutual field in such a way that
it would be predisposed to become
structured and embodied more so you're
saying that there's some way of holding
those kind of like peak experiences that
would help it to embody into the life
beyond that peak experience is that yeah
absolutely
like yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah I mean
well you know speaking it's interesting
we're kind of running an experiment here
where I live at the monastic Academy
because we do circling retreats and
circling practice are you familiar with
circling is it yeah yeah so it's a kind
of inner subjective conversational
meditation style and you know we're we
do week-long retreats where all we do is
circle together and we definitely reach
states of kind of collective coherence
that are peak experiences and outside
the norm of what we experienced in a
week-to-week day-to-day but then we
immediately go back into our work life
our practice life together here at the
center and what I notice is that it
definitely impacts the the kind of just
the kind of like psychic social
infrastructure of trust and love and
patience and willingness to do things
that you don't want to do for the sake
of the whole and all the things that
make a community like this actually
flourish and I wonder the degree to
which the but you what you notice about
how these peak experiences don't
necessarily then land in the world so to
speak is due to the fact that so many
people do that kind of work in drop-in
groups right where they're just kind of
encountering each other for a brief
period of time for a weekend or a week
and then they kind of my experiences you
then try to like make it work using
online communications or maybe you even
do like a semi-regular group if you all
live in the same place but that is not
the same as living together in a
community where you're you know just
have to make it work because there's no
escape and so I I haven't I haven't
noticed as much of a discrepancy here
the the one that you referred to
probably though because of the the kind
of you know the structure and the
schedule and fact we all live together
yeah yeah that's interesting that could
be make a big difference I think to me
this
a bit of an analogy to the question of
personal experiences and assimilation of
those experiences I live in a horror of
getting at the end of my life and all
the peaks all the insights they all just
were for a moment and fell away I never
kept any now pardon likes the surrender
and gliese but another part of me thinks
yeah my job is not to get into
epiphanies my job isn't something back
from epiphanies mm-hmm yeah poof yeah I
mean that's that's real tough yeah
that's that's as the teacher here at
Maple Banasik Academy says that's really
the rub of the spiritual path to a large
degree is letting letting go of your
insights without forgetting them yes you
and I struggle with that pretty much
every day I'm not very good at yeah it's
like breathing I mean something comes in
and then you let it go back out but you
hope you got something in addition to
what you released yeah but it's so easy
to have an insight and and then it just
completely evaporates and doesn't leave
a mark on your life yeah I've had it
happen to myself many many times and
then I almost have to have that insight
again and I was and and I know lots of
people I mean lots of people who come
here have insights and then just it's
like nothing happened but something did
happen but nothing happened really it's
a there's a beautiful tragic moment
where you have an epiphany and you're
like oh and you realize you've had that
epiphany before and so what yeah well
that's that's what I mean though with
the good conversations and I mean that
to me why the a form of good
conversation is the kind of conversation
where we hold each other accountable to
our realizations right that like yeah
you a part of the way that we don't
forget our insights is is through
accountability and through community and
through naming it
people that we want the respect of you
know things like that and so yeah that's
a big part of where I think like my
solitaire practice kind of grounds into
my life in community the social aspect
is is definitely one of the features
that helps the anchoring process what
about what about your family do you have
good family conversations what's your
childhood background in conversation
well I'll state you know my family
nobody and my feelings interested in
these topics it's like I had my mom
who's like an incredibly intelligent
woman you know professor
well everybody my family is a professor
both my sisters and both my parents and
I had my mom she listened to one of my
podcast episodes and it just did not get
anything she was like that this all
sounds like nonsense to me basically but
I'm happy that you're that you enjoy
these conversations and so the the kind
of content wise there's not much of a
there's not much symmetry of interest I
guess you could say but you know I think
certainly I grew up given that my
parents were both perfect they would
often talk about ideas at the dinner
table and so there was this kind of like
just love of concepts I think that was
implanted in me is from a very young age
that I've struggled with because like
spiritual people quote-unquote aren't
all wrong like obviously concepts are a
problem if they're held incorrectly but
but I also you know it's that you don't
let throw the baby out with the
bathwater and so that was definitely a
big part of my childhood and it's
probably a large degree to why I can
kind of swim in these multi-perspective
waters the way I can spiritual people
are all wrong says Daniel Thorson
when you say like that oh geez I'll have
one of those things at the bottom of the
screen where it quotes you in terms of
producing material online who do you
like who do you admire who do you
think's got good content or who do you
think's got the the aesthetics and the
setup that you like who do you look to
who do you listen to yeah I mean in
terms of like professionalism obviously
rebel ISM is just killing it I learned a
lot from talking with David and kind of
seeing just how they managed to make
everything look so professional in terms
of where the center of gravity and the
conversational space is I mean I just
got a 785 day silent solo retreat so you
know not totally on the cutting edge but
it seems like Peter Lindbergh with what
he's doing with de stoah has really
pushed the whole field forward is the
sense that I get and in general I love
his approach to conversations and his
attitude I think that it's right on the
money as far as I'm concerned I do
though think that in general oh how can
I say this in a way that's not annoying
I wish I wish people in our in our in
our neck of the woods were a little bit
more earnest in our media ecology you
know I find today my earnest I would
like to wear my heart on my sleeve like
this is this is all about being of
service to the world to sentient beings
that's that's Buddhist parlance but like
coming out of retreat I feel like why
are we having some of these
conversations I think for me if it's not
about either be
coming more able to be of service or of
directly serving the world then what
what is this and maybe this is a way of
saying you know in meta modern terms
there's the irony and sincerity kind of
like oscillation I wonder if we're if we
haven't yet found our way to a real
grounded sincerity that we can trust and
I wonder where that will come from and
how we can rely on that and take that
seriously and be willing to kind of like
have these conversations with our heart
open maybe and yeah something like that
yeah I do think this sincerity side lags
little on the sister irony I part of
that is probably because just the long
history of pre-modern especially but
pre-modern and modern forms of sincerity
so like it's hard to be ironic in terms
of flexible and meta and you know maybe
you can post metaphysical things like
that to do that and really feel like
you're taking things seriously when
everybody whoever took anything
seriously was doing it with these huge
totalizing assertions yeah well so
what's your what's your take on how you
discover a kind of I love that term post
metaphysical sincerity like what'swhat's
all wrapped up in that I think there's
probably two things and one of them is
just the emotional component is if
you're better with your emotions or if
you skew conversations like I think
asking people what they hope is a good
way to getting their earnestness but
another part of it is a kind of
foreground background flip where we've
tended to think there's viewpoints and
then there's some kind of space between
the viewpoints that maybe we tolerate
maybe we don't but if we thought of the
space between the viewpoints if we
thought of the inter perspectival space
as the real solid grounds not the
mysterious airy in between that's what
we all know it's solid we can have
confidence in that we can go forward and
then we can tell each other that we can
have all the profundity of the past
maybe more from that space of not having
to believe in insist yeah yeah that that
resonates yeah
yeah there's some kind of like that's I
think that's that's the trick is there
some kind of sincerity in emptiness
there's some kind of sincerity in the
theater like nature of the whole thing
that I hope we all can turn into because
I think it's actually really an
important part of these conversations
having a potency yeah yeah it's it's
hugely important to me but I'm seldom in
discussions where it makes sense to
bring it forward
I'm very often it's such a arcane or
contentious topic that you get derailed
into weird considerations which aren't
that's not a bad thing to do but it's
it's only seems like it's a space where
somebody who already basically gets it
can talk to somebody else who already
basically gets it and that's where you
go yet we're both right here this is
this is really something we can work
with this it spread nonsense I'm not
sure I'm not sure I understand like
where how does it derail typically or
what's the here's the thing I was uh I
was the guest on a philosophy salon a
few days ago I wanted me to talk about
post metaphysical spirituality I
actually wanted to get into my theory of
the dynamics of spirituality but we
never got there because the idea of
spiritual experience and practice versus
belief was such an interesting concept
that everybody wanted to weigh in and
wonder about it and they hadn't heard it
that way before
some people had it as aggressively like
how can you say that the whole point of
spiritual traditions is that belief is
what works there's just a lot of issues
for people and also it's a very new
concept for a lot of people yeah yeah
yeah railing but there's a lot of prep
work yeah yeah well that's I mean oh boy
so within one of the approach
spiritual practice that I do is kind of
a emerging spiritual approach called the
soul making Dharma created by Rob rupiah
they talk about they call it feminist or
Temenos which is a kind of spiritual
container where you can actually have
these deep experiences of sincerity and
beauty and divinity and sacredness with
other participants but in order to
create that container you actually need
a whole list of prerequisites everything
from emotional sensitivity and kind of
capacity and energy body sensitivity all
the way to act to ontological symmetry
right you need actual epistemological
coherence in order to have these
experiences and have them be held in a
way that allows them to flourish and not
be taken advantage of or derailed as you
say and so I hear you there's like a lot
that goes in to having the kind of
experiences that I longed for and that I
hope that we can somehow they can
somehow find their way into into media
then for me I'm interested in yeah that
sense of energy sensitivity of a somatic
generalized somatic interoception or
whatever we might want to call it yeah
that's huge
to me that's you know a very route
practice for establishing a container
that works and takes me forward Lee now
I get a whole series of interviews with
people on spiritual transmission and
most of them sort of ignored my
questions about that and felt like you
know the higher consciousness is given
by grace and it doesn't have any
specific requirements and some people
have that somatic sensing and some
people don't and I'm like okay look I'm
gonna ponder that but in my experience
you don't get very far or or if you
don't have that and you go forward you
go forward with only part of yourself
yeah yeah 100% agree with you I don't
know if you noticed my slight kind of
like I felt taken aback that people
would but you can I mean that's just so
not inconsistent with my experience it's
all about this energy
body this body of energy whose body or
soma soma is where this all goes down
I mean but then again you know varieties
of human experience who knows maybe
there's other ways to go about it but I
don't think so that I mean hang my hat
somewhere I feel that so yeah I feel
pretty that's a pretty defensible place
to hang it what about politics what do
you think are the social analogies to
all these processes and ideas the social
key I'm not sure what you mean by like
what how about this what kind of
political and socio-economic setup in
society do you think best supports
interpersonal and individual development
of practice oh my god Waymon better a
question answer reinforcing right right
[Music]
just let that drop in and see what wants
to come out so here's if I give it a
little more framing for you might help
I'm sure you could make a conservative
argument and say that people who want to
preserve traditional lifestyles and
traditional values are keeping up the
context in which our ancestors have
always done their development of meaning
and their spiritual transformation and
that you've got to have you know church
like structures you've got to have
strong social codes you've got to have
like smaller communities you've got to
have you know the divine called out in
the political system you've got to be
wary of new innovations because they
don't necessarily tap into that ancient
genetic mythological spiritual history
that's manifested in traditional customs
there's the conservative art the
progressive argument is what uni is more
generalized and distributed well being
if you want somatic activation you need
everybody to have more secure and
healthy bodies they've got to eat right
they've got to have medical insurance
that they don't have to stress about all
the time
you gotta take some of the basic
problems off the table so people can
flourish yes yeah yeah well I mean I I'm
much more personally sympathetic today I
think the liberal argument that you just
stated I would say for my piece to say
something that perhaps isn't as commonly
said in these kinds of arenas is that I
think one of the things that is hmm
might help this along is if we start
revivifying concepts like the soul and
like God and the sacred and finding ways
to hold them in this irony ironic
sincerity such that they can have power
again so that nature can be sacred and
so that life can be sacred so the beauty
can be sacred you know and and that as
we empower those and kind of find our
desire to live in a way that creates a
beautiful soul then I think that the
social systems will start to it will
start to become clearer which social
systems in social context are anathema
to this whole like if you if you walk
into a modern hospital with the
perspective of what amplifies and what
dampens this it's a terrible place to be
it's a terrible place to be even though
death is right there next to this all
it's very confusing and you could
imagine reconstituting or just even
making all kinds of shapes to a hospital
to make it a little bit more soulful and
for me that that would feel like you
know it's just an interesting way into
thinking about what you what you brought
up
they just make me think of the last time
I was in a hospital which was my father
was in a coma
around Christmas he's he's with my
brother in Indonesia now so his
recoveries been terrific but he was dead
ish but it's interesting to be in those
hospital room spaces and to see what
your actual options are for creating a
change in mood and bit of the case in
there yeah not much knowledge a little
bit I mean most people do nothing so you
have you can bring in color you can
bring in sound you can bring in love but
the structure itself places a lot of any
conditions on that yeah yeah yeah so
just making making making room for soul
both in our own minds and hearts but
also like in conversation and in systems
when we can I think that's a big part or
it's a big part for me it's a big part
of where my I think passion is moving
yeah yeah that's a tricky one because
there may be other dynamics in other
zones you know if I it's a big part for
me too but it sometimes I wonder if
that's just my specialization you know
and what would be how would you rewrite
the rules of a legislature to make its
outputs more soulful regardless of the
people who were involved I don't know
yeah totally uh and and I would not at
all suggest that this is like a kind of
totalizing narrative right it's not it's
not all about soul but for me I think
it's a leverage point that I'm I'm keen
to get more familiar with because I
partly because I grew up as a
non-religious and spend a lot of time as
an atheist and so even the idea of
looking in this way is quite new to me
and is is very rich and opening a lot of
beauty and meaningfulness in my life and
so I think I'm most it's mostly a
reflection of where I'm not personally
not that it's a panacea a means the you
know spiritual religious life is
interesting to me I've always been
skeptical and upset
with it and at this point I'm I'm kind
of agnostic about whether anything's
really there I actually don't care
whether there's any prior realities that
I'm dealing with it would work on it but
it also works fine if there isn't
because there's a very easy model in
which the integration of different parts
of myself builds up into a surplus
resonance that I can then relate to in
some fashion as a higher sample higher
other a higher energy or whatever and it
integrating me it produces a wholeness
that is equivalent of my soul and I can
also see there's a subtle analogy where
if people come together and different
genres of culture come together they get
a similar effect and they call it
religion they they divinized something
about their culture right and that's
that we're absolutely fine with no
pre-existing ontological necessities now
they may or may not be there that's a
different discussion right it doesn't
have to be a god we need to experience
God but I've experienced God and it
looked like he was really there
yeah well also looks like these these
trees outside my window are really there
but they're not they're empty and any
god that exists is empty too is so yes
also no I am NOT I guess see this is why
you create containers in which there's
ontological clarity when I talk about
soul when I use that word I do not mean
a self existing entity but there's none
of that to be found as far as I'm aware
anywhere but we can still just like all
these other non self existing entities
that impact us Phoebe we can still play
with the ideas hold them in ways that
impact us deeply and open up landscapes
of meaningfulness and beauty and soul
even though that isn't a thing
apparently there doesn't seem to be a
thing baby
you know agnostic about whether that's
the thing it was very at least yeah that
agnosticism real nor not real well they
say in Buddhism this is they say they
say the middle path is it's neither real
nor not real that's the razor's edge and
I mean that is a that opens up into a
very broad highway
experimentation in clay I think if you
if you walk it carefully so that got a
middle path approach you know Anna
Garden is turning of the wheel yeah it's
really profound it's the grandfather of
Sam the thing I like I've heard people
try to analyze Arjuna's form of logic
compared to Aristotle's form of logic
and I feel like they're missing points
in it I feel like what he's doing is
taking his feeling attention back and
forth over a distinction until that
distinction transcendentally blurs out
and I'm going to see that the descendant
of that kind of cognitive approach in
the Zen tradition where you do go man
and forth across a distinction where
it's almost seems impossible that these
two things should coincide but as you
keep going back and forth something
happens to you hmm I love that yeah yeah
that seems true or useful way of looking
at it yeah right well a podcast again
what would you what would you love to do
like what if your resources to make
online content were suddenly doubled or
something like that
Wow except for you suddenly doubled
would not actually be that much well
imagine a number that actually provides
a significant number of some kind yeah
yeah I would love to travel to different
you know emerging experimental neo
monastic communities and make like a
video series about what I find there and
kind of try to weave a network between
those spaces particularly like people
that are experimenting with Ecology's of
practice and a really deliver away like
we hear it we are here at the monastic
Academy my sense is that there's that
we're at the very beginning of a
planetary Renaissance when it comes to
those sorts of spaces and I would love
to open up pathways of learning between
the
nodes you know Jim refers to them as
kind of like proto B communities proto
game B communities and I yeah I
sometimes dream about you know somehow
moving from community to community
learning and sharing best practices
between all of them and that would be
wonderful but besides that I mean the
nice thing about what I could do is this
very low low costs so I I don't know
that I'd want to make it much bigger in
any way yeah it would be nice to travel
in a different context with it I go to
visit my mother in Puerto Rico and her
husband was in a Gurdjieff Ian group
that lived in the tropics for equal they
were part of the people cool eyes her
project together back in the day right
on the people who were in the community
and who've left they stay in touch but
they're they're like post community
they've all got reflections now and
they've balanced it with other parts of
their lives those people really
intrigued me you know when they get
together at for dinner saying I would
love to be able to record and
orchestrate that dinner a little bit hmm
the people who've blossomed out of the
specific context they were in but still
bring all that stuff with them what
would intrigues you about that that
perspective or that um here's what I
love but I'm fascinated by the dynamics
of the communities I'm fascinated by the
practices effectiveness I'm concerned
about the limitations of groupthink in
particular languaging and I'm very
interested in how specific bodies of
teaching and practice rub up against the
complexity of the rest of our lives
yeah people who've come out of the
context but are still connected to it
are in a real nice position to tell you
something yeah so true I mean I'll tell
you so I where I live now
I lived here about four years ago for
two years and then I left and moved back
to Boulder where I've lived off and on
for two years before I came back and
that that time in between I actually
recommend that people who have been here
for some years I recommended
leave because it's like you say leaving
space like this just completely
transforms your relationship with it
whether you come back or not and it's
just yeah you're right
maybe that would be fascinating to talk
to get it gathered with the people who
had spent significant time in community
and have them reflect on and what that
was like
and Gurdjieff en communities are so cool
- so maybe excellent yeah they're really
uh they have a lot of unusual ways of
going at it and I know enough of them
that I do I can see all the ways they
disagree with each other some
communities think that the the fourth
way is totally contaminated by whose
fence keys phrasing I don't know that
means anything just read gorgeous books
don't read any of the other stuff and
other people like start with our general
understanding of the community and home
there's a lot of back and forth yeah
yeah beautiful I mean I love that
diversity I think yeah that's wonderful
that's all right Daniel Thorson what do
you think we should talk about next I'll
tell you I'm really happy that we
haven't talked about Cove it really
happy about that everybody wants to know
what I think about Cove it because I was
in retreat well it happened I've been
just learning about it and so I want it
I don't want it I don't want this to be
an opening to talk about it but I
wouldn't appreciate you for not talking
about I don't know I mean I I guess I
didn't really Reese do a lot of research
on this project before I stepped into
this space I'm not sure what with what
feels saline I think I'm feeling more
curious about your perspective I I know
that you written for the interval review
and you had a couple I think articles in
the post metaphysical special edition
which I know about Fatah worried and so
I am I there's a part of me that just
wants to kind of fall down the post
metaphysical spirituality rabbit-hole
and in particular like I have a personal
interest
in drawing connections between that way
of looking and the approach that I
mentioned before the soul making Dharma
because I see that as a kind of
paradigmatic post metaphysical spiritual
praxis and so I am I'm very curious
about what symmetries exists there but I
also don't know that make for very
compelling media content well anybody
could stop listening at this point if
they want to it's interesting stuff I
like to go into it you know briefly and
intensely and come back out and I like
to dwell too long in that really there's
just some intense beautiful Byzantine
philosophical and logical approaches
involved you know trying to figure out
the relationship between whether things
have the equivalent of an inherent
essence despite the fact that all our
experience of them is relative and
conditioning
you know how much what can you take as a
given even even given that you're
approaching the world through the types
of meditative contemplative and
spiritual techniques that people have
used throughout history and they've used
them in the context of assuming all
these Givens that's an interesting
question to me but I'm focused on most
is how do you describe the
phenomenological validity and
effectiveness of practice found in
spiritual and religious traditions
without making any assumptions about
what exists oh that's so good yeah how
do you well my my tendency is to think
of it as an orchestration of functional
sub components to produce a surplus
resonance which we can then interact
with well as we've produced it and
that's individually that looks like a
higher thing about
collectively it looks like thing about a
community and we can look at an extra
thing through different lenses we could
look at it through a first-person lens
and say well that's my higher or deeper
experience of myself we look in a second
person lens and say it was as if it was
a higher person or entity that I related
to look at it objectively and say it was
as if it was a higher energy or
experience I was drawn into hmmm these
options but they all play off this thing
that can be produced in our experience
by certain kinds of practices and I
think it's plausible to find the
through-line in very diverse spiritual
practices of of combining our subjective
systems by like my body or the chakras
or left and right or our perception of
ourself and our perception of the other
or our perception of the consciousness
and our perception of the world like
these are all subjectively active
systems that we have within us and most
cheerful practices involve some enhanced
coordination between these subjective
systems to the point where it succeeds
into a numinous extra that we then have
valuable seems so pleasant for me I
guess if we wanted that correspond to my
understanding in in my world of one type
of practice of like Samadhi practiced I
had harmonized all of the systems as you
say and that in the retreat I just did
the I was practicing with the approach
of jonno so that would produce a kind of
like numinous experience of the jhanas
perhaps although in buddhism obviously
that's not understood as being
transcendental it's just a very refined
material experience but the
way that I have resolved that problems I
helped design the curriculum here at the
monastic Academy and one of my
curiosities is how do we talk about what
happens when you do these practices
intensively without using the
epistemologies of the dominant culture
like materialism or you know rendering
interpret the self gets or something
like that and typically the way that I
talk about it is as that we're playing
with perception we're learning how
perception works that's it that's
actually all we're doing is that we're
we're learning how to participate with
our perception in ways that either
relieve suffering or amplify
meaningfulness that's it that's you know
and so you can in that way I do I find
this equative like it's quite a simple
way to not make any unnecessary claims
but still retain the potency because it
turns out the perception is empty and
you can just play in that space and it
includes everything you know it turns
out that everything is perception so
it's it's very inclusive way of
presenting things to how does that it's
clear I don't see any irresolvable
problem between that and what I just
said maybe think of different approaches
to perception and how they can be
conceived of as coordinating these
different parts so for example right
intentional attention exercises where
you're gonna focus on purpose or sustain
a purposeful focus that allows a lot of
parts to come together on the same
project in the way that riding a bicycle
involves many like lateral things being
drawn together in the forward motion
it's also a kind of like if I just
wanted to perceive everything in an open
way in order to do that I have to dial
down things I'm privileged in my focus
and kind of dial up things I'm not
privileged a kind of equilibrium our
parsimony patients yes
right yeah now they're in a position to
be balanced together I'm already
perceiving them but now I'm trying to
perceive them with relatively equivalent
focus and that's where they can start to
blend together to produce this slightly
more than the sum of its parts thing
that might come forward to me are those
conditions of practice yeah well but I
guess my question for you then is or hmm
I'm it again play my my biases is that
you know what it's all about is about
deeper and deeper realizations of
emptiness the empty nature of things of
procession I I don't it's not obvious to
me how that fits into your the way that
you're constructing it is it like so so
yes you can harmonize different systems
within your experience but fundamentally
liberation happens to the degree that
you see you know systems and all those
perceptions and all those even the
harmony itself and all that so what how
does that square let me take emptiness
in at least three directions on the one
hand yeah there's the assertion of the
ontological emptiness of things right is
that assertion justified or not we don't
know emptiness itself is empty of
emptiness yes right and and to some
degree enos the cognitive idea of
absence might be problematic right there
might be a knee allistic hint in some of
that phrasing depending on who you're
talking to about
secondarily one way to think of
emptiness is as an extra present quality
which exceeds the objects of cognition
and that's an description of this
numinous more than the sum of its parts
right you've got all the things then
there's this other something whether we
call it a penis or energy or presence or
God or whatever it's just not any of the
things and it allows those things to be
full of themselves and also to be
coordinated but it also isn't limited by
any of the combinations of those and
then the third way I go at it is in
order to achieve higher coordination of
the parts
you need more spaciousness right same as
if your muscles were all not your
functional coordination is decreased
you've got a spacing out so like when
you see the atoms that make up the
molecule now there's another whole range
of coordination x' to consider
everywhere you find this extra
spaciousness if you found the
availability to an enhanced coordination
that you hadn't considered before huh I
love that yeah yeah I mean that it's it
would be I would like I don't think I
feel like we have time to go all the way
into this but I would love to sit down
with you sometime and just really
explore I feel like I want I have a
desire to reconcile my under like the
system that I practice in with what
you're saying and it would be I think it
would be fun for me to do as a kind of
game but I don't know we don't want to
do that right now
yeah I would love that let's do that
because these are some of the pool the
most passionately interesting topics in
my heart yeah well one thing I will say
though I'll be curiously just on this
one one one piece is that the first part
that you said around whether or not
emptiness can be considered a kind of
ontological truth it you know from where
I'm coming from it that matters less
than whether or not adopting it as a
provisional truth liberates and that
much I think that we can be quite
confident in and so that again is why I
think it's of great benefit to ground
everything in perception because then
ontology actually becomes inactive
within the context of using different
ways of seeing to interface with
perception or to perceive differently
and emptiness then is just one method of
experimentation that just happens to be
really baller and good you know
resolving occasional hypothesis of
emptiness has produced a great number of
significant results over the millennia I
would probably tweak the description
there a little bit and say that what's
producing the results in my mind is the
addition of the hypothesis of emptiness
to the normal experience of the
cognition of the universe so that what
you've got are two systems at play and
you go back and forth between them and
that blending is another nation that
produces this excess effect that's cool
that's cool that's how you get a pick up
a form in emptiness
yeah you get a non-duality yeah yeah
let's totally do that sometime yeah yeah
I'll reach out I mean this is something
that I I'm coming out of retreat really
curious about because what so uh my
teacher here at the monastery is a Zen
teacher Soria for all but the teacher in
my heart like the night kind of my root
teacher my heart is robber baya and he
just passed away three weeks ago and he
constructed this I've interviewed him
like four times I'm like I guess I think
I've interviewed him more than anybody
else and he has built I believe the most
elegant and practical approach to
deepening an understanding of emptiness
and I find it just endlessly beautiful
and one of my one of the things I feel
committed to is really kind of pushing
that into more spaces and seeing how it
rubs it up against other ways of
looking at these kinds of topics and
really sort of like yeah fine fine
tuning my understanding fine tuning like
the system because he's no longer with
us so it has to for me I wanted to be
carried forward somehow and I feel like
I can help do that so I would love to
play with you and see what we can ever
gather let's get together and mutually
fine-tune ourselves around the theme of
emptiness all right let me try to bring
this back to podcasters and then segue
out of here sure I usually ask at the
end what would you ask the next person I
talked to someone who's also involved in
trying to bring interesting ideas and
approaches through in an online format
hmm what would you be curious about from
their experience yeah I'd be curious if
they ever if they ever think about
stopping and if they do why and if they
do and they keep going why because I
think about I think about wrapping up my
project pretty regularly yeah that's
nice no one has suggested that yet but I
bet it's pertinent to the feelings of a
lot of people doing this hmm I've got a
radio show too every week I think yeah
look how much longer am I gonna keep
doing this
haven't I said it already yeah exactly
yeah well this has been terrific I'm
heaven I'm loath to stop because I'm
having a really nice time with you but
we've got the promise so I can let it go
and an hour and a half is enough for
anyone listening to listen to yeah
pleasure to meet you layman I've seen
you online and I'm really happy that
we've had a chance to connect and I've
enjoyed this commerce come on I felt
that it's been like it's funny coming
off retreat I feel like I'm like booting
up the conceptual
territory of the conversational spaces
that I've participated in like over the
last couple years like I let go I just
forgot all about it was under treatment
so I wasn't thinking about the stuff but
this has been a really lovely way I
think to kind of like boot load a little
bit more of that so thank you for
helping me find find this self again
today and yeah look forward to more
connection and conversation
[Music]